# Michael Sparks

NYC

michael.sparks13@gmail.com | 918.269.6064 michael-sparks13.github.io/portfolio

Seasoned product management expert with a decade-long tech journey, now pivoting towards GIS, cartography, and climate. Fuelled by a passion for storytelling through maps and armed with a master's in Digital Mapping. Ready to blend expertise and enthusiasm in a new role focused on protecting the environment.

### **EDUCATION**

University of Kentucky, Dept. of Geography, 2022-2024

Masters of Science in Digital Mapping

Yale University, New Haven, 2009-2013

Bachelor of Arts in Psychology

#### **EXPERIENCE**

CrowdedParks.Org - Creator, Engineer, Writer

2021 - Present

- Created a site to focus on promoting the protection of public lands as a way to mitigate the climate crisis
- Independently conceived, designed, and coded the entire site. Incorporated mobile-first design, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, and DOM manipulation.
- I have written multiple stories on topics ranging from crowding in the national parks to how parks are preserving ecosystems under threat from climate change
- Interviewed dozens of park officials, scientists, park visitors, government officials, and academics, including traveling to Maryland and California to interview park superintendents

## National Parks Traveler - Contract Writer, Climate & Parks

2021 - 2023

- Cover climate change and America's National Parks for the number one site for national parks news.
- Articles include sea level rise's impact on parks, how parks are adapting to electric vehicles, and how parks recover from extreme weather events

#### The New York Times

Senior Product Manager, Growth

2021 - 2023

- Lead group focusing on transforming the New York Times' access model and audience segmentation products
- Collaborated with stakeholders across the business and newsroom teams to launch Subscriber Only Newsletters—the first paid feature in NYT history
- Identified gaps in audience targeting and ran AB tests that improved subscriber conversion by 27%

2019 - 2021

- Directed a 10-person team through multiple design and AB test iterations to build an entirely new landing page for the Home Delivery product that increased conversion by 10%
- Led a 25-person team that built country-specific pricing and increased subscriber conversion by 200% outside of the U.S.

#### The Knot

Lead Product Manager, Guest Zone

2018 - 2019

- Defined product strategy and roadmap in collaboration with top management and a cross-functional working group
- Prepared and conducted user research, including NPS surveys, demographic surveys, user interviews, and data analysis that led directly to a 3X increase in guest list usage
- Used data segmentation to identify sources of user error, then led team that designed & introduced features to reduce user error rate by 85% in The Knot's online RSVP tool
- Work with the executive team to lead diversity and inclusion initiatives across the company, including anti-bias training & new hiring processes

Senior Product Manager, Mobile

2016 - 2018

- Coordinated cross-functional team through new product inception, launch, and multiple iterations to grow mobile users 250% YoY
- Evangelized for and helped implement a company-wide shift to "Mobile first" by leading "App Academy,"
  & mentoring product managers to use mobile best practices

#### Life360

Senior Product Manager, Monetization

2014 - 2016

- Promoted to larger scale priority for the organization, driving initial monetization and product re-branding efforts for the company. Doubled sign-ups to the app's paid service within 6 months.
- Executed AB tests to test hypotheses and uncover insights about user behavior. Used results to influence management on the future direction of Life360's monetization efforts.

Product Manager, Localization

2013 - 2015

- Product lead on Life360's international product to launch the company's i18n strategy. Grew international user base to more than 30MM within 16 months.
- Launched partnership with Yahoo! Japan to localize Life360 in Japan and deliver 5 MM downloads over 2 years

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Web development, GIS, Front End Design, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Python, Mapbox GL JS, Mapbox Studio, SQL, Bootstrap, Git, GitHub, QGIS, Cartography, Data Visualization, Geospatial Data Analysis, Adobe Illustrator